让我们回顾一下本讲座中的一些重要概念。
Let’s recap some of the important concepts from this lecture.
首先，有一些非常重要的公约。首先是所谓的右手坐标
Firstly, there are some very important conventions. First is the so called right-handed coordinate
帧。当我们构造一个三维坐标系时，我们需要正确构造它
frame. When we construct a 3-dimensional coordinate frame, we need to construct it properly and
我们用右手指导我们。x轴与我们的拇指对齐，y轴对齐
we use our right hand to guide us. The x-axis is aligned with our thumb, the y-axis is aligned
用我们的食指和z轴用我们的中指。谈到描述
with our index finger and the z-axis with our middle finger. When it comes to describing
围绕轴的旋转方向，我们想象我们正在抓住那个轴
the direction of rotation around an axis, we imagine that we’re grasping that axis
用我们的拇指指向箭头的方向和我们手指的方向
with our thumb pointing in the direction of the arrow and the direction that our fingers
绕轴线卷曲表示正旋转方向。
curl around the axis indicate the positive rotational direction.
三维旋转矩阵可以用3×3矩阵和列来描述
A rotation matrix in three dimensions can be described by a 3 x 3 matrix and the columns
该矩阵的单位矢量是与坐标系B的轴对齐的。第一个
of that matrix are unit vectors that are aligned with the axes of coordinate frame B. The first
列是帧B的x轴，第二列是帧B的y轴和第三列
column is the x-axis of frame B, second column is the y-axis of frame B and the third column
是框架B的z轴。并且，我们使用此旋转矩阵从框架旋转矢量
is the z-axis of frame B. And, we use this rotation matrix to rotate a vector from frame
B到框架A.有三个基本旋转矩阵
B to frame A. There are three elementary rotation matrices
其对应于围绕x轴，y轴和z轴的旋转。我们可以创建一个
which correspond to rotation around the x-axis, the y-axis and the z-axis. We can create an
通过使用这些基本序列在任意两个坐标系之间进行任意旋转
arbitrary rotation between any two coordinate frames by using a sequence of these elementary
旋转。实际上有12种可能的旋转序列。一个重要的警告，欧拉的一部分
rotations. There are in fact 12 possible rotation sequences. An important caveat, part of Euler
旋转定理，就是没有两个连续的旋转可以绕同一轴。这个的
rotation theorem, is that no two consecutive rotations can be about the same axis. Of this
在图12中，这些序列中的6个被称为欧拉角。它们包含两个旋转
12, 6 of these sequences are referred to as Euler angles. They contain two rotations about
相同的轴，但不是顺序的。例如，旋转大约x，然后，y，然后再旋转x。虽然
the same axis, but not sequentially. For example, rotate about x, then, y, then x again. Although
所有这六个技术上都是欧拉角，当使用术语欧拉角时，人
all six of these technically are Euler angles, when the term Euler angles is used, people
通常是指特定的序列，ZYZ。但是，这种惯例因不同而异
are generally referring to the specific sequence, ZYZ. But, this convention varies across different
工程学科。因此，确保与某人交谈时很重要
disciplines of engineering. So, it’s important to be sure when you’re talking to somebody
关于欧拉角，你说的是完全相同的序列。
about Euler angles that you’re talking about exactly the same sequence.
其他六个被称为万向角。并且，经常提到其中两个
The other six are referred to as Cardan angles. And, two of these specifically are often referred
作为滚动，俯仰，偏航角度。万向角具有围绕三个不同轴的旋转。
to as roll, pitch, yaw angles. The Cardan angles have rotations about three different axes.
我们可以用任何一个来描述旋转
We can describe the rotation from any one
在单个旋转方面框架到另一个，围绕某个轴旋转角度θ
frame to another in terms of a single rotation, a rotation by an angle Theta about some axis
V.并且，我们讨论了在给定旋转矩阵的情况下确定Theta和V的技术。和，
V. And, we’ve discussed techniques to determine Theta and V given a rotation matrix. And,
我们介绍了Rodriguez方程，它允许我们从轴和角度走
we introduced the Rodriguez equation which allows us to go from an axis and an angle
回到旋转矩阵。我们介绍了四元数。这些都是超复杂的
back to a rotation matrix. We introduced quaternions. These are hypercomplex
数字。它们实际上包括标量和三元素向量。单位幅度四元数
numbers. They actually comprise a scalar and a three-element vector. A unit magnitude quaternion
它被称为单位四元数，可用于编码旋转。而且，那里
which is referred to as a unit quaternion can be used to encode rotation. And, there
是一些简单的规则来确定四元数的倒数和复合两个四元数，
are some simple rules to determine the inverse of a quaternion and to compound two quaternions,
我们可以计算出两次连续旋转的效果。
and we can work out the effect of two consecutive rotations.
出现的一个重要问题是为什么我们使用像旋转这样的东西
An important question that comes up a lot is why do we use something like a rotation
矩阵。旋转矩阵是3乘3矩阵，它包含9个数字，但我们知道
matrix. A rotation matrix is a 3 by 3 matrix and it contains nine numbers, but we know
根据欧拉定理，我们只需要三个数字-三个角度-来描述一个旋转。
from Euler’s theorem that we only need three numbers - three angles - to describe a rotation.
当我可以使用三个时，使用九个数字有什么好处？
What’s the advantage of using nine numbers when I could just use three?
嗯，重要的是，旋转矩阵不仅仅是任何旧的3乘3矩阵。这是具体的
Well, importantly, the rotation matrix is not just any old 3 by 3 matrix. It is a specific
矩阵。它是一个正交矩阵。所以，虽然有九个元素，但有一些
matrix. It is an orthonormal matrix. So, although there are nine elements, there are a number
约束。实际上有六个约束条件，这使我们只有3个自由度。
of constraints. In fact there are six constraints, which leaves us with only 3 degrees of freedom.
第一个约束是该矩阵中的每列是单位向量。事实上，
The first constraints are that each column in this matrix is a unit vector. In fact,
每列是一个单位向量引入了三个约束。然后，列是
that each column is a unit vector introduces three constraints. And then, the columns are
它们彼此正交并引入另外三个约束。
all orthogonal to one another and that introduces another three constraints.
旋转矩阵具有一些非常方便的属性。首先，我们可以复合姿势
The rotation matrix has some very convenient properties. Firstly, we can compound poses
或简单地通过乘法旋转。对于欧拉角度或滚动，俯仰，情况并非如此
or rotations simply by multiplication. That’s not the case for Euler angles or roll, pitch,
偏航角度。第二个非常重要的好处是
yaw angles. A second really important benefit is that
旋转矩阵的列描述新坐标的x，y和z轴
the columns of a rotation matrix describe the x, y and z axes of the new coordinate
框架就旧的而言。另一个重要的特性是你可以实际读取一个旋转
frame in terms of the old one. Another important property is that you can actually read a rotation
矩阵。旋转矩阵的列根据单位矢量x，y来描述
matrix. The columns of the rotation matrix describe in terms of unit vectors the x,y
和新坐标系的z轴。让我们来看看其中的一些不同
and z-axis of the new coordinate frame. Let’s have a look at a few of the different
我们讨论过的旋转表示。我们可以有一个9的旋转矩阵
rotational representations that we’ve discussed. We can have a rotation matrix with its nine
数字在里面。而且，旋转矩阵的一个优点是没有可能
numbers in it. And, one of the advantages of rotation matrix is that there is no possibility
有一个奇点。我们谈到了奇点，万向节问题以及随之而来的问题
of having a singularity. We talked about singularities, the gimbal problem, and that occurs with
欧拉角或滚动，俯仰，偏航表示方向。
Euler angles or roll, pitch, yaw representation of orientation.
复合两次旋转很容易。对于旋转矩阵，我们简单地将两个矩阵相乘
Compounding two rotations is easy. For a rotation matrix, we simply multiply the two matrices
在一起，而对于三角表示，它是非常重要的。我们也可以考虑一下
together, whereas for the three-angle representations, it’s nontrivial. We can also consider that
我们可以用两个向量表示坐标系的方向;一个方法向量和一个
we can represent a coordinate frame’s orientation by two vectors; an approach vector and an
方向向量。这只是六个数字。这是奇点自由，但不是很容易
orientation vector. That’s just six numbers. It’s singularity free but not very easy
复合以这种形式表示的两个方向。我们还可以考虑角度+轴
to compound two orientations expressed in this form. We can also consider the angle + axis
取向。我们有一个数字来描述旋转量，角度和我们
orientation. We have one number to describe the amount of rotation, the angle, and we
需要两个数字来表示旋转轴。它是三维的单位向量，
need two more numbers to represent the rotational axis. It’s a unit vector in three dimensions,
所以它里面只有两个唯一的数字。这种表示是免费的，但是
so there are only two unique numbers in it. This representation is singularity free, but
表示零旋转有点问题。而且，再一次，复合两个
it’s a bit problematic to represent a zero rotation. And, once again, compounding two
轮换是不平凡的。最终表示是单位四元数。它有四个数字，
rotations is nontrivial. Final representation is the unit quaternion. It’s got four numbers,
虽然只有三个是独一无二的，因为它有一个单位量级。这是奇点
though only three of them are unique because it’s got a unit magnitude. It’s singularity
自由。并且，我们引入哈密顿量积作为两个四元数乘法的方法。所以，
free. And, we introduced the Hamiltonian product as a way of multiplying two quaternions. So,
在某些方面，四元数有很多优点，奇点自由，代表
in some respect, the quaternion has got a lot of advantages, singularity free, represented
通过较少的数字，可以使用较少的算术将两个四元数相乘
by a fewer numbers, and two quaternions can be multiplied together using fewer arithmetic
操作比矩阵乘法的情况。在机器人技术中，它确实如此
operation than is the case for matrix multiplication. In robotics, it’s really
常用的顶部和底部表示，旋转矩阵和
the top and bottom representation that are in common use, the rotation matrix and the
单位四元数。最后，我们可以代表姿势，它具有
unit quaternion. Finally, we can represent pose, which has
通过单一的均匀变换得到平移分量和旋转分量
got both translational component and a rotational component, by a single homogeneous transformation
矩阵-一个4x4矩阵。相对姿势的组成通过乘以矩阵来完成。否定
matrix - a 4 x 4 matrix. Composition of relative poses is done by multiplying matrices. Negation
或者通过反转矩阵来完成逆相对姿势。请记住，反转同质
or an inverse relative pose is done by inverting the matrix. Remember that inverting a homogeneous
转换矩阵不是通过转置来计算的。这只是一个属性
transformation matrix is not computed by taking its transpose. That’s a property only of
旋转矩阵。并且，将矢量表示的点从一帧转换为
a rotation matrix. And, transforming a point represented by a vector from one frame to
另一种是通过将点的均匀表示乘以同质来完成的
another is done by multiplying homogeneous representation of the point by a homogeneous
变换矩阵。最后要记住的是，协调帧
transformation matrix. Final thing to remember, coordinate frames
是你的朋友当您尝试描述复杂问题时，请使用大量的问题。连接
are your friend. Use lots of them when you’re trying to describe a complex problem. Attach
它们对每个感兴趣的对象都写下它们之间的关系
them to every object of interest and write them the relationships between the coordinate
帧。一些关系可能是不变的。其中一些关系可能会
frames. Some of the relationships might be constant. Some of those relationships might
是时变的。并且，请记住，NASA使用它们。他们一定很好。
be time varying. And, remember, NASA uses them. They must be good.